Ronald Perera Papers, 1966-2002
Smith College Archives
Ronald Perera Papers
1941-[ongoing]
Perera, Ronald.
RG 42 UUID:a68d13c9-7e79-4e15-987d-4cfd6cf6c127
5 boxes (4 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Papers include a small amount of biographical material on Perera, such as his career summary and resume, reviews, flyers and programs, photographs and newspaper articles. The majority of the materials are musical manuscripts of works by Perera.
Biographical Note
Ronald Perera was born in Boston, Massachusetts on December 25, 1941. He received both his B.A. and M.A. from Harvard, where he studied composition with Leon Kirchner. From 1963 to 1965 he served as Operations Officer on an ocean mine sweeper, and was honorably discharged with the rank of Lieutenant, USNR. In 1967, while on a John Knowles Paine Traveling Fellowship in Music from Harvard, Perera studied electronic music and computer composition with Gottfried Michael Koenig at the University of Utrecht, Netherlands. He also worked independently with Randall Thompson in choral music and with Mario Davidovsky in electronic music.
Perera's teaching experience includes two years at Syracuse University, where he taught music theory and held a research associateship in electronic music (1968-1970), a year as Acting Director of the Dartmouth College Electronic Music Studio (1970-71) and thirty-one years at Smith College (1971-2002) where he has taught music theory, composition and electronic music, and where he has held the Elsie Irwin Sweeney Chair in Music since 1983.
Ronald Perera's compositions include operas, song cycles, chamber, choral, and orchestral works, and several works for instruments or voices with electronic sounds. He is perhaps best known for his settings of texts by authors as diverse as Dickinson, Joyce, Grass, Sappho, Cummings, Shakespeare, Francis of Assisi, Melville, Ferlinghetti, Updike and Henry Beston. Seven major pieces are represented on recently released compact discs.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Ronald Perera Papers contain materials spanning Parera's career. The size of the collection is 4 linear feet. The papers contain a small amount of general information on Perera, such as his career summary and resume, reviews, flyers and programs, photographs and newspaper articles. The majority of the materials are musical manuscripts of works by Perera.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
Records are open to research according to the regulations of the Smith College Archives.
History of the Collection
The materials in the Ronald Perera Papers, which form part of 42. Faculty Biographical Files, were donated by Perera in 1996 and 2002.
Search Terms
Perera, Ronald.; Smith College--Faculty.; Composers--United States--20th century.; Music--Instruction and study--Massachusetts--Northampton.
- General
  - Career summary and resume 1986, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Price listing: scores and recordings 1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reviews 1973-1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper articles 1988-1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Flyers and programs: The Outermost House and The Yellow Wallpaper 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs
    - Six of performance of The Yellow Wallpaper 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Two of Ronald Perera and students in the electronic music studio 1973, n.d. (Box 1)
    - Four of Ronald Perera in studio 1988-1991 (Box 1)
- Musical Manuscripts
  - The Yellow Wallpaper n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Araboolies of Liberty Street n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Three Love Lyrics n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Golden Door: for mixed chorus and chamber ensemble, full score n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Triptych: for organ n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Golden Hymn: original manuscript n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Piano Suite: pencil original 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Did You Hear the Angels Sing?: adapted from the poem, "Christmas Carol" by Samuel H. Miller, pencil originals n.d. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Summer Songs: Five songs on poems of Emily Dickinson for medium voice and piano pencil originals n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Apollo Circling: Four lyric songs for medium voice and piano on a poem by James Dickey 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reflex: for viola and tape, pencil originals 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Three Night Pieces: for soprano, alto solo, women's chorus, solo cello, piano and percussion (one player) 1975 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Fantasy Variations: for electronically prepared piano 1975 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Crossing the Meridian: pencil originals n.d. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The White Whale: theater music for baritone and orchestra; correspondence regarding score notes on suggested orchestra arrangement n.d. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Canticle of the Sun: for narrator, mixed chorus and digitally synthesized instruments (electronic tape) 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Sleep Now: songs for high voice and piano on poems of James Joyce 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Shakespeare Songs: for high voice and piano 1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Five Meditations on Wondrous Love: for organ 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sun's Rising: for organ 1986 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Three Waltzes for Four Hands 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sonatina for Viola and Piano 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fanfare: for viola and piano 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Augmented Forces: to Ken Fearn and John van Buskirk 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Out of Shadow: for piano 1988 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Music for Flute and Orchestra: sketch scene 1990 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - The Saints: three pieces for orchestra with audience participation pencil originals of sketch scene and full score n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - The Outermost House: four choruses of mixed voices with narrator, soprano solo and chamber orchestra 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Five Summer Songs: on poems of Emily Dickinson 1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - A Fondness of Music: for women's chorus and piano n.d. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - The Writer: for soprano and five instruments from Visions for two sopranos and chamber ensemble 1993 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Mass 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Visions: sketches and full score n.d. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - The Outermost House: original full score; four choruses of mixed voices with narrator, soprano solo and chamber orchestra 1991 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - S.: Original conception and artistic collaboration by Mark Harrison. Adapted from the novel, S., by John Updike 1988 (Box 4)
    - sheets 1-75 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - sheets 76-149 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - sheets 150-224 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - sheets 225-305 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - S.: An Opera in Two Acts: Score - Orchestra Version. Based on the novel by John Updike. n.d. (Box 4)
    - Act I
      - sheets 1-90 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - sheets 91-180 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - sheets 181-270 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - sheets 271-360 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Act II
      - sheets 361-431 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - sheets 432-501 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - sheets 502-571 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - sheets 572-642 (Box 5, Folder 8)